So today's דף daf *daf* is ל"ה *lamed hey*, 35, but we
pick up on ל"ד עמוד ב' *lamed daled amud bet* and we
have been discussing the משנה mishna. *mishna* that talks about different ways
that somebody cuts intentionally the מום Mum, *mum* away or whatever,
then or excuse me not cuts away, that's cuts away either the
sign of leprosy or intentionally makes the מום Mum *mum*, that we
fine him and different ways of considering how to do the fine.
One is very sort of pragmatic and talks about what are we
going to do to create a disincentive, and the other is more
of a formal way which we just sort of negate the effect
of his action. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a couple of
wrap-up questions. בעי רב פפא *ba'ei Rav Papa*, so this is about
15 lines down, it's a line after the line beginning with the
ו' *vav* in brackets, starts with the word קציצה *ketitza*. So בעי
רב פפא *ba'ei Rav Papa*, רב פפא *Rav Papa* asked, יטהר תנן
או ויטהר תנן *yitaher tenan o ve-yitaher tenan*? When it says that
if somebody cuts away a spot of leprosy, then he has to
wait till he gets another spot of leprosy, could wait his whole
life for that, and then when he becomes טהור *tahor* from that,
he will become טהור *tahor* from the first one. So the question
is how do you read the text? Does it say when he
gets another spot of leprosy and becomes טהור *tahor* from it, then
he will be טהור *tahor*? Or does it say when he gets
another spot of leprosy he will be טהור *tahor* from the first
one? What makes him טהור *tahor* from the first spot that he
cut away? The advent of the second spot, now that we have
a new one we basically erase the first one, or is it
the purification of the second one? Now the question is who cares?
Either way he's טמא *tamei* because of the second one, so who
cares if it's the advent of the second that erases the first
or it's the purification of the second? Either way he's going to
remain טמא *tamei* until the second one becomes purified. So טהור *tahor*,
so let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what difference does
it make. So יטהר
תנן *yitaher tenan*,
now he has to become טהור *tahor*, so he still remains טמא
*tamei* even with the second, או ויטהר *o ve-yitaher*, when he, I'm
sorry, no, יטהר תנן *yitaher tenan* that the advent of the second
makes him טהור *tahor*, או ויטהר תנן *o ve-yitaher tenan* when he
becomes טהור *tahor* from the second he becomes טהור *tahor* from the
first. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says למאי נפקא מינה *le-mai nafka mina*, who
cares? Either way you're still טמא *tamei* right now because you have
the second one. לחתן שנראה בו נגע *le-chosson she-nira bo nega*. If
a bridegroom, who's just come from my brother-in-law's wedding so very appropriate,
if a bridegroom has no spots of leprosy there by the way,
has a spot of leprosy, דתנן *de-tenan* we taught in the משנה
mishna. *mishna*, חתן שנראה בו נגע *chosson she-nira bo nega*, if a
bridegroom has a spot of leprosy, נותנים לו שבעה ימים *notnim lo
shiva yamim*, you give him seven days before you rule on his
leprosy because until a כהן Kohen *kohen* declares it as טמא *tamei*,
even if it genuinely satisfies the criteria, he is טהור *tahor*. So
out of respect for his personal שמחה *simcha* you do not actually
make a decision until after the seven days of the חתונה *chasuna*,
of the שבע ברכות *sheva brachos*. לא *lo*, for him, ולביתו ולכסותו
*u-le-beito u-le-kesuso*, or even for his like cloak and his garment, right,
even if they have leprosy you do not deal with it until
after his, until after the שבע ברכות *sheva brachos* are over, the
seven days. וכן ברגל נותנים לו כל ימי הרגל *ve-chen ba-regel notnim
lo kol yemei ha-regel*. Similarly for any person, not a חתן *chosson*,
you wait till after a יום טוב *yom tov*. If it happens
on יום טוב *yom tov* you wait till after the whole seven
days of יום טוב *yom tov*. So there'd be a case where
you could get a second spot of leprosy and you're not yet
טמא *tamei* because we're giving you a week. So therefore does the
second spot of leprosy itself purify the first and then you'll actually
have a week where you're טהור *tahor*, or do you have to
wait till the second is purified before you're purified from the first
and then you don't get this week off? So what do you
say? אי אמרת *ei amart* יטהר תנן *yitaher tenan*, the advent of
the second spot makes you טהור *tahor* from the first again. Why,
what happened to the first? You cut it away. So there's no
way of us actually dealing with the first but we're going to
treat it as if it's still there until the second spot. So
if the advent of the second spot makes it as if the
first one has now been overridden, so מקמייתא טיהר ליה *mi-kamaisa tihar
lei*, from the first one you become טהור *tahor* because you got
the second spot. לבתרייתא נטרינן ליה שבעה ימי משתה *le-basraisa natrinan lei
sheva yemei mishta*, and for the second one we're going to give
you seven days till the wedding week is over. So you actually
are טהור *tahor* for this week until we look at the second
one. אלא Ella... אי אמרת *ella ei amart* ויטהר תנן *ve-yitaher tenan*,
if we read it that when you become טהור *tahor* from the
second then you become טהור *tahor* from the first, סוף סוף כאילו
מטמי ליה לבתרייתא הא מטמי וקאי מקמייתא *sof sof keilu metamei lei
le-basraisa, ha metamei ve-kaimi mi-kamaisa*, even if you're not going to rule
on the second one you remain טמא *tamei* from the first one
until the second one becomes טהור *tahor*. So you're not going to
get the week off. So מאי *mai*, what's the story? תיקו *teiku*.
Okay, so we leave that as an unanswered question. That's just wrapping
up the issue of צרעת tzaraas *tzara'as*. Now we get back to
our issue of בכור bechor *bechor*
and that if you make a מום Mum *mum* we negate your
action. So and we fine you. Again, whether the fine is of
a more formal sense of negating the action or more to actually
practically create a disincentive and therefore not letting you ever שחט Shecht
*shecht* this בכור bechor. *bechor*, that is debated in the משנה Mishnah,
*mishna*. So בעי מיניה רבי ירמיה מרבי זירא *ba'ei minei Rabbi Yirmiyah
me-Rabbi Zeira*. So רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* asked רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*,
צורם אוזן בבכור ומת *tzorem ozen be-bechor u-meis*. Let's say a person
punctures the ear of a בכור bechor? *bechor*, again the ear particularly
because that doesn't heal and we'll also see in the next משנה
Mishnah, *mishna* why this might be a classic example. You puncture the
ear of a בכור bechor. and somebody does and he dies. מהו?
mahu? מהו לקנוס בנו אחריו? mahu liknos beno achrav? Will you fine
the son afterwards? So this is particularly because we look at this
as a קנס. knas. So if we look at it as a
קנס, knas, it's a punishment to you for your actions. So if
the person who did it is dead, maybe there's no purpose of
punishing the actual, you know, transgressor. He is dead. Now of course
you could say not everything is about punishing the person. Some things
are about creating societal disincentives, so therefore you never want anybody to
benefit from this, right? Because if so, you know, some guy's on
his deathbed, he figures, oh, now's the right time, and he goes
and he punctures all the ears of the בכור Bechor so that
his kids don't have to worry about it. Meaning there could be
other reasons other than just punishment. But and you know, and not
everything is conceptualized as a קנס, knas, as a type of a
fine. You know, even the way the גמרא Gemara said it before,
there are different types of understandings of what a fine means. Does
a fine mean, you know, is it to prevent similar types of
behavior in the future? Is it to punish the person, you know,
as a sense of, you know, justice? So anyway, this is a
general question about when you have fines, does it apply to the
son afterwards, to the children afterwards? And let's take a look. The
גמרא gemara actually lines this up and compares it to a couple
of cases. This is a question raised in a couple of different
מסכתות. masechtot. These cases are always the ones that are looked at.
And this is the basic question: do we say קנסו בנו אחריו
knasu beno achrav or not? Now, so let's take a look at
how the גמרא gemara sort of compares it. So it says like
this.
So אם תמצא לומר, im timtzo lomar, if you were to say
מוכר עבדו לכוכבים ומת, mocher avdo l'kochavim umet, that's another example we
look at. If somebody sells his servant to a non-Jew, because that
servant is obligated in מצוות, mitzvot, and by selling him to a
non-Jew, you actually prevent him from performing his מצוות. mitzvot. חז"ל Chazal
said that you have to redeem him, buy him back from the
non-Jew, even if it costs ten times the original sale price. So
that's now, so let's say that person died. Will his son have
to buy him back? If you were to say in that case,
ומת קנסו בנו אחריו, umet knasu beno achrav, the son would be
fined and would have to buy him back. That's because בכל יומו
ויומו מפקע ליה ממצוות. bechol yomo v'yomo mafkei lei mimitzvot. Every day
that עבד eved is prevented from doing מצוות, mitzvot, which really means
that the reason we would apply it to the son is not
so much that it's an idea of punishing you, but it's a
concern for the עבד. eved. So because it's a concern for the
עבד eved and we want him to now be able to do
the מצוות mitzvot and he's in a position and he can't, so
therefore we're going to demand that he be redeemed. So it's really
not about punishing and therefore we will apply it to the son.
That would be that case because we obviously are concerned about the
welfare of the עבד. eved. אם תמצא לומר, im timtzo lomar, now,
if you say כיון דאוחדה במועדה ומת לא קנסו בנו אחריו. keivan
moachda b'moada umet lo knasu beno achrav. Let's say I have a
whole field that I have to plow or whatever I have to
do,
and I say, heck, you know, I'll wait till חול המועד, Chol
HaMoed, I'm off from work anyway, and I'll take care of it
then, or I'll have more time, I'll take care of it then.
And why will I be allowed to take care of it? You're
not allowed to do מלאכה melacha in חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, but
you're allowed to do it if it's דבר האבד, davar ha'aved, if
it's going to be a loss of money. Okay, but of course
when חז"ל Chazal allowed it for a loss of money, that was
when it was out of your control. If you intentionally plan on
scheduling your stuff for חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, they דוקא davka did
not want you to, you know, in order to plan your work
for חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So they said you're not allowed to
in that case plow it. Now, of course it's very funny that
we're framing that as a fine. You could just say that that
doesn't warrant the exception of דבר האבד. davar ha'aved. Right, דבר האבד
davar ha'aved is when you couldn't control it, not when you could
control it. So again, all of these are funny the way the
גמרא gemara is framing it as a fine, and you could always
make an exception on any one of these cases by saying conceptually
it's not a fine. But it's
saying, okay, so we could say one case you have to, not
because we know the general rule is you punish the son, but
you have to because of the concern for the slave. In the
other case you don't have to, not because in general we're not
concerned about punishing the son, but here the father really hadn't done
anything wrong yet to begin with. You know, the transgression didn't even
happen yet. So what about our case? הכא מאי? hacha mai? What's
the story in our case? Where you had father actually did do
something wrong, he made a wound in the בכור. Bechor Okay, there's
not like some situation that has to be actively resolved and salvaged
like the case of the slave. So do we punish the son
for the sins of the father or not? Sounds very biblical. So
anyway, so what do we say? הכא מאי? hacha mai? לדידיה קנסו
רבנן. ledidei kansu rabanan. The
father—for him, the rabbis fined, דלא הוי, d'la hvei, and he's not
around, so we can't punish him. So, okay, the son is off.
או דילמא o dilma לממוניה קנסו רבנן. lemamonei kansu rabanan. No, they
didn't say we're punishing you. We're saying this property you can no
longer benefit from, you cannot get benefit from, you know, from the
wages of sin. והאי איתיה vehai itei and the property is still
around. Now again, the way I sort of conceive of framing that
as could be a formal sense, did we punish him or did
we say something about the בכור? bechor. Also, by the way, that
could fit in the משנה. Mishnah If basically you say we negate
your actions, it's like it doesn't have a blemish, then we made
a statement about the בכור. bechor. If we say you can never
benefit from it, maybe that's more about saying something about you. So
it could be raised as a formal issue. Did we direct our
statement towards you or did we say something about how we're looking
at the animal? You could also look at it as a policy
question. Is it about punishing the person or is it about, you
know, preventing these types of things from being done and therefore you
don't want to limit it just to the malfeasor? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא gemara says what's the story? Does it
apply to the son or not? והאי איתיה vehai itei and the
money is still around. אמר ליה amar lei תניתוה, tanituha, we taught
it in a משנה. Mishnah, שדה שנתנקשה בשביעית, sadeh shenitnaksha bashvi'it,
let's say you basically picked up all of the weeds, you didn't
actually pull the weeds, which would be really working the field, but
you picked up, you know, the thistles and the thorns and you
cleared the field on שמיטה shmita which again, you're not supposed to
do but it's not a real מלאכה. melacha. You know, it's like
you raked the field, you picked up all the thorns and the
sissels. You didn't actually work it. What?
You mean that already fell off?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So you're clearing it on שמיטה shmita so you
can plant it on מוצאי שמיטה. motzaei shmita. Okay, but you didn't
actually work the field. You just cleared it. Okay, so תיזער למוצאי
שביעית tizarei l'motzaei shvi'it then we allow you to plant it after
שמיטה shmita because you didn't really work it on שמיטה. shmita. What?
It does something, but it's not real מלאכה. melacha. ניתייבה nityayva נידיירה
nidayra
let's say however you manured it, one is sort of you brought
in barrels of manure, the other is נידיירה nidayra you brought in
animals and you penned them there so that they would actually defecate
and, you know, and fertilize it by them, you know, naturally. In
those cases, which is actually sort of working and improving the land
on שמיטה, shmita, לא תיזער למוצאי שביעית lo tizarei l'motzaei shvi'it you
can't do it after שמיטה. shmita. And again, this is conceived of
as a fine, as a punishment for your transgression. ואמר רבי יוסי
בר חנינא ve'amar rabbi yossi bar chanina נקטינן naktinan
we take the position, הטיבה ומת hetiva vamet
if the person actually improved it,
yeah, not manure, but I mean which is what you're doing, but
fertilized it, thank you, fertilized it and died, בנו זורעה beno zor'ah
his son actually can plant it on מוצאי שמיטה. motzaei shmita. אלמא
alma you see לדידיה קנסו רבנן ledidei kansu rabanan we fine him,
the person, לבריה לא קנסו רבנן livrei lo kansu rabanan not the
son. And presumably even though the person, the father did the transgression,
and presumably the same is true here. And again, the thing is,
okay, but what types of things are you going to even define
as a fine, as a קנס knas to begin with, as opposed
to defining something as a תקנה, takana, you know, where, you know,
things that are sort of for, you know, preventative rather than fining?
But if we're defining it as a fine, then we're saying to
the person who transgressed, yes, to his children, no. Okay, now, אמר
אביי amar abaye now of course even that isn't really an answer
because there you could say,
right, it's one thing by the sheep to say we look at
it as though it still, as though it doesn't have the blemish.
And formalistically we can negate your actions and then it would relate
to the son as well. Whereas by the field, what are we
going to say? We're going to look at it as though it's
not fertilized? I mean, by the field we have to be more
action-oriented than object-oriented. Right, don't do this. So there we're more talking
to the transgressor. Whereas by the sheep you could say we're looking
at it as though the blemish isn't there.
You mean you say there's no blemish when there is a blemish?
Exactly. That's what the גמרא gemara says, לממוניה. lemamonei. So therefore in
a formal way we can actually look, say we're not going to
acknowledge that blemish and therefore it would naturally apply to the son.
Whereas here we're going to relate to an action, you are not
allowed to do this. So since it's an action, there's a you,
there's the subject, and therefore it wouldn't apply. So anyway, there's a
lot of ways to distinguish. Do we conceptualize it as a קנס,
knas, what's our policy issues, how do we formalize it? But the
גמרא Gemara sort of puts them all in the same category. אמר
אביי amar abaye now the גמרא Gemara takes it one step further.
Said אביי, abaye, נקטינן naktinan we take the position therefore, טימא טהרותיו
ומת. tima taharotav vamet. Here's a case where really it seems like
it should be about policy. Somebody went, this is the case in
גיטין gittin and was מטמא, metamei, impurified somebody else's תרומה. terumah. He
took a שרץ sharetz and he threw it on somebody's תרומה terumah
pile. Now, impurified, impurified somebody's pure תרומה. terumah. Okay, now that makes
it worthless or almost worthless. The problem is you can't collect payment
because it's היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, it's not visible. You
don't see the טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
if you did it intentionally you have to pay. Now let's say
the guy who did that died. Would his son have to pay?
So he says, now we're going to say, לא קנסו בנו אחריו
lo kansu beno acharav the son wouldn't have to pay. מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama היזק שאינו ניכר hezek she'eino nikar לא שמיה היזק. lo
shmei hezek. Non-visible damage is not technically damage. קנס דרבנן הוא, Knas
Derabanan Hu, it's only a rabbinic fine.
דידיה קנסו רבנן, Didei Kansu Rabanan, לבריה לא קנסו רבנן. Lebrei Lo
Kansu Rabanan. They fined him, they did not fine his son. Now
there's clearly a case where you should say we're not just looking
at this as a punishment, you know, this is if you would
almost like a correction in the laws of נזק, Nezek, the same
way there's a concept of גרמי Garmi and so on, this is
too big of a loophole and therefore, you know, and also there's
somebody that's out money. This guy is out a thousand dollars, so
he should remain out his money just because this guy died? You
know, so there's like obviously in a lot of these cases questions
about do we just look at it as a punishment or what
are the other types of ways to frame it and the other
policy considerations and so on. But the גמרא Gemara here is sort
of looking at this all as a type of a קנס Knas
and thinking that there's a general rule of לא קנסו בנו אחריו,
Lo Kansu Beno Acharav, and that is the general rule, that when
we have a קנס Knas we generally do say לא קנסו בנו
אחריו, Lo Kansu Beno Acharav, which makes sense if it's a punishment.
But the real question is what things are we going to choose
to define as a קנס Knas and what things are we not
going to define as a קנס. Knas. So anyway, תוספות Tosafot discusses
it, there is other סוגיות Sugyot about it, but this is a
very central גמרא Gemara in terms of that discussion.
כפל Kefal is also a קנס. Knas.
Right, so that's also a מחלוקת, Machloket, right,
as to whether it's a קנס Knas or- well, no,
כפל Kefal is definitely a קנס. Knas. Right, right, but then there's
a question about העמידו בדין Ha'amido Badin or not העמידו בדין, Ha'amido
Badin, right? So that's true also about biblical קנסות Knasot
as well. Okay, so anyway, so but the real- the first real
key question is what do you define as a קנס Knas versus
do you define it as something else? All right, now we move
on, keeping in- keeping right- keeping in the what do you call
it? The discussion about if you intentionally make a מום, Mum, therefore
the rabbis had to say that you cannot- like we said, you
cannot benefit from that. We look at it at minimally as though
the מום Mum was not made. Okay, whether that means you'll never
be able to שחט shacht this animal is a different question, but
minimally it's like the מום mum was not made if it was
done intentionally. And now we're going to discuss exactly what intentionally means.
Let's take a look.
משנה, Mishnah. top of למד-ח עמוד א. Lamed-Chet Amud Alef. מעשה בזכר
שפריחיו זקנין, Maaseh Bezachar Sheperuchav Zkenin, there was a story about a
certain
old goat- not goat- sheep, like a ram,
very old, ושערו מדולדל, Vesaro Meduldal, and its hair, its wool was
like, you know,
trailing, scraggly, like there was a lot of, right, you know, it
was very, very hairy because it had never been sheared because it
was a בכור bechor, that didn't have a מום, mum. so they
couldn't do anything with it, they couldn't shear it, so it never
had a haircut, it was like a
שמשון. Shimshon. Okay, וראהו קסטור אחד, Vera'ahu Kastor Echad, and a certain
like Roman general or you know some type of an officer, not
general, officer saw it, ואמר Ve'amar and said to whoever the shepherd
was or the owner was, מה טיבו של זה? Mah Tivo Shel
Zeh? What's going on with this sheep? It's never been sheared in
its life. אמר לו, Amar Lo, so they- the people said to
him, בכור הוא, Bechor Hu, it's a- it's a firstborn, ואינו נשחט
אלא אם כן היה בו מום, Ve'eino Nishchat Ela Im Ken Hayah
Bo Mum, and it can't be shechted unless there's a blemish, there's
never been a blemish, so that's what's happening and we presumably also
can't work- shear it until there's a blemish. So what did he
do? נטל פיגום, Nato Pigum, he took some type of a spear,
וצרם באזנו, Vetzaram Be'ozno, and he made a hole in the ear.
By the way, notice the name of the spear is a פיגום,
Pigum, it's a classic example
of making a blemish in a בכור bechor is פוגם אוזן של
בכור. Pogem Ozen Shel Bechor. So I'm wondering if it came from
this story, okay, let that become the or maybe not, maybe the
reason it's a classic מום mum, is because that's the easiest way
to make a blemish that won't really, you know, damage the animal
and at the same time will be un- won't heal.
It almost sounds like a
story- it does, it definitely is. And what also is- sometimes you
have a story but often it's a story about a תנא. Tanna.
מעשה ברבן גמליאל, Maaseh Berabban Gamliel, you know, מעשה בזקני בית שמאי
וזקני בית הלל, Maaseh Beziknei Beit Shammai Veziknei Beit Hillel, right, here
it's just like random people. Right, I know, it's very- it is
very strange.
I mean, it's a Latin- pugio is a knife with two- two-
a double-sided blade.
Okay, aha, all right, there you go. So that's a פיגום Pigum
is a pugio. Okay, while we're at it, what's a קסטור? Kastor?
Quaestor. Quaestor, of course! Oh!
Now, okay, yeah that I remember from when I studied Roman history.
I don't. What's a quaestor?
Some- revenue officer essentially.
Exactly. But what- yeah.
All right, part of the justice system.
Part of the
justice system.
Oh, so you think that this is like sort
of an in- I don't know, no, I don't know, but he
was some person in
the legal system.
ובא מעשה לפני חכמים והתירו, Uva Maaseh Lifnei Chachamim Vehitiru, they said
fine, it's מותר. Mutar. Okay, now why would you say it's מותר?
Mutar? It seems from the story, I would have assumed, but we'll
see not that way, certainly not the way רש"י Rashi reads the
משנה, Mishnah, that even though he did it intentionally, he figured he
would be nice and help out the Jews, but you didn't do
it and you didn't ask him that wasn't perhaps even your intent,
you asked him a question, he gave you an answer, so we're
not going to fine you for something that he did. That's what
you would assume, but let's keep on reading. Okay, ואחר
שהתירו, Ve'achar Shehitiru,
and after they said it was permissible, הלך וצרם באזני בכורות אחרים,
Halach Vetzaram Be'oznei Bechorot Acherim, he figured, "Heck, I'll be a צדיק,"
Tzaddik, and he went around to other people's, you know, whatever sheep
and started making holes in their ears. ואסרו, Ve'asru, and then they
said it was forbidden. Now, again, up- If you read this simply,
it means now their policy going to perhaps say it is always
forbidden because once you allow it, it'll lead to somebody going ahead
and doing it all the time even if it's a non-Jew and
so on. But again, the way רשי Rashi reads it and seems
the way the גמרא Gemara, reads it is not that way. It's
that the first case maybe he didn't realize that it was going
to make it allowed, although you know what he did. But then
why would he do it? I know, I don't really understand it
well. But once he heard that they were actually saying that it
was allowed then he and then he was doing it, then it
was clear maybe he had some doubt, he didn't know if it
would help or not, but he wasn't certain that it was going
to be an act that allowed it. After he heard it, he
knew it was going to be an act that allowed it and
then he did it, then it's being done intentionally for the sake
of making it allowed and then it's forbidden. Read that way by
the way it becomes also very interesting considering our discussion a minute
ago about קנס. k'nas. Who are they fining? Right, nobody asked him,
they're not fining him. So it's really much less about קנס k'nas
than about again like, you know, either society, you know, sort of
a policy issue or negating the effect of the action. It's not
really about a fine.
Okay. Why's it מותר mutar for your son if he did?
I understand. That's the point I'm saying. That it's funny that the
גמרא Gemara before framed it as a fine where it doesn't necessarily
seem that way.
And there's a contradiction. Okay, so I don't know.
So let's keep on reading. Okay. פעם אחת היו תינוקות משחקים בשדה.
Pa'am achas hayu tinokos mesachakim basadeh.
Now once there were kids who were playing out in a field,
וקשרו זנבי טלאים זה בזה vekashru zinvei telaim zeh bazeh and they
tied the tails of sheep together. Right, wouldn't that be fun seeing
the sheep sort of pulling at each other? Not very kind, I
think, but that's what the farm kids did before you had TV.
ונפסקה זנבו של אחד מהן venifsaka zanavo shel echad mehen
and one of their tails got pulled out, okay. That makes it
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. והרי הוא בכור. vaharei hu bechor. It
turned out that it was a בכור. bechor בא מעשה לפני חכמים
והתירו. ba ma'aseh lifnei chachamim vehitiru. They allowed it because that certainly
was done without any intent. ראו שהתירו, ra'u shehitiru, they saw that
it was permissible, that they permitted the בכור. bechor They weren't such
תינוקות, tinokos, you know, who knows, they might have been who knows
like fifteen, or something, teenagers. ראו שהתירו והלכו וקשרו זנבות בכורות אחרים.
ra'u shehitiru veholchu vekashru zanvos bechoros acheirim. They figured heck, we'll help
other people, they started doing that with other people's sheep. ואסרו ve'asru
and then they forbidden it. Now again, from this, if you simply
had this משנה Mishnah. you would have thought that it meant that
we won't even now permit it on a one-off thing because once
we allow one case, then it gives license and people come to
do it again. But רשי Rashi and the גמרא Gemara is going
to read this as no, the first case if it was just
a one-time thing and people really didn't know, we will continue to
allow it. We're only not going to allow then the next act
because that was implicitly done with knowledge. So it's not like from
here on in we have forbidden these cases, we only forbid them
after once somebody becomes aware. And that they tie in to the
next line of the משנה, Mishnah, זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is
the
principle. כל שהוא לדעתו אסור שלא לדעתו מותר. kol shehu l'da'ato asur
shelo l'da'ato mutar. When it's done with your knowledge then it's forbidden,
not with your knowledge is permissible. So again presumably the way it's
being read is that the first event was not done with an
awareness that it would make it permissible. The second event was done
with that awareness and forbidden. But again, it's very strange that about
the case of the non-Jew that it's not the question about the
owner's awareness, although we'll see a little bit about that in the
גמרא, Gemara but about the non-Jew's and therefore to frame it as
a קנס k'nas becomes a little strange.
The first time he did have awareness.
I know, that's the problem. רשי Rashi tries to claim that he
didn't. רשי Rashi says, well he didn't know really what the effect
of his action would be. Who you know, he didn't know that
the rabbis would allow, maybe he even thought it had a מום
mum on its own, of course if that were true why bother.
So, yes, so you know, yeah, it is difficult. You could try
to read it that in the first case, which fits it more
along the lines of the קנס, k'nas, that it's a question about
whether the owners knew. You know,
but the second case would always seem to be all about the
kids and not about the owners regardless of
the רחמנות rachmanus on the on the goat.
Oh, very well.
But afterwards the second time he was
so
meaning in both cases it was להתיר. l'hatir. To benefit I see.
To distinguish between you're trying to להתיר l'hatir it for the help
of the owners or להתיר l'hatir it for the sake of the
sheep, maybe. Yes.
I was trying to also reconcile that with the שבת Shabbat case,
like didn't we say that if a non-Jew comes and comes on
a light for you, you said you can't sit there?
Yes. So let's take a look.
Because you know but over here we see that you at least
get you know you can get benefit the initial time.
Right, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara about that.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, פעם אחת, pa'am achas,
וצריכא, utzricha, you need both cases of the קסטור kastor and of
the kids. דאי אשמעינן עובדי כוכבים de'i ashmeynan ovdei kochavim had you
just had the case of the non-Jew, דלא אתי למסרך, delo ati
l'misrach, there if we allow it, meaning here you're telling me why
it was a חידוש chidush in both cases that we allowed it
the first time. Because by the non-Jew we wouldn't have a concern
that, although it turned out we were wrong, logically we wouldn't have
a concern that if you do it once it's going to lead
to further actions. It was a freak occurrence, he acted, he figured
he'd be a צדיק, tzadik, he helped, whatever, it's not going to
lead to him doing it again. If you tell kids, Jewish kids,
that they can do that it's okay, it will more likely lead
to a repeated offense, okay, or doing this intentionally the second time.
Now, one the concern would be therefore, you know, undermining the institution
of בכור, bechor the other concern that רשי Rashi also says is
are we just concerned about a חינוך. chinuch. concern that somebody's doing
wrong things? So for the non-Jew, even if he would do it
again, he's not doing an עבירה. aveira. It's not an עבירה aveira
for him, but for Jewish kids to do it, it is an
עבירה. aveira. So therefore, to say to allow it for the non-Jew
we're not so concerned, as concerned about what will happen afterwards. אבל
קטן דאתי למיסרך, Aval katan de'ati lemisrach, but a kid that once
you do it once he'll do it again if you allow it,
אימא לא, eima lo, maybe we wouldn't have allowed it even the
first time. ואי אשמעינן קטן, Ve'i ashmeinan katan, if you said a
קטן katan משום דלא אתי לאחלופי בגדול, mishum dela ati le'achlufi begadol,
just because we're allowing the kid, it won't lead to an adult
to come to do it. So even if somebody does it, they
won't do the עבירה aveira of intentionally making a מום. mum Now
again, is that really our only concern is the עבירה aveira or
is our concern the sort of undermining of the, you know, sort
of of the institution, undermining of the, you know, of the sense
like, you know, the בכור bechor, is hands off, of the sense
of... so, but that's the way the גמרא Gemara is framing it
at least, that if you let a kid do it, again so
I guess it was under בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, they were smart
enough to know that they would help people by doing it again,
but they were under בר מצווה, bar mitzvah, you won't necessarily have
an adult coming and doing it and doing an עבירה. aveira. אבל
עובד כוכבים, Aval oved kochavim, if you allow the non-Jew even the
first time, דאתי לאחלופי בגדול, de'ati le'achlufi begadol, so if the non-Jew
can do it, I can do it, and therefore I'll intentionally make
a מום, mum. אימא לא, eima lo, צריכא. tzericha. Therefore you need
both cases.
So I understand, now all of this is again strange because the
question is how are you conceptualizing what the problem is? Is it
that we really don't want בכורות bechorot to be done, it's not
because we don't want you to do the עבירה, aveira, right? We
just want to protect the idea that a בכור bechor. is not
something anybody should make a מום mum in, and therefore, you know,
it's sort of protecting the institution, which sort of seems to be
the case more from this משנה. Mishnah. But again, the גמרא Gemara
in line with its sense of קנס knas is more at least
focusing on the, it would seem, the עבירה aveira concern rather than
the fact that a בכור bechor, is having a מום mum made
in it. And therefore it's able to distinguish between whether it leads
to חינוך chinuch problems, adults doing it and so on. Just the
phenomenon of it happening doesn't seem to bother the גמרא Gemara as
much as the question of the עבירה. aveira. Okay, so that's consistent
with its approach to look at this as a קנס. knas. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב חסדא אמר רב קטינא, Amar
Rav Chisda amar Rav Katina, getting to Michael's question, לא שנו אלא
דאמר ליה, Lo shanu ela de'amar lei, אלא אם כן היה בו
מום. ela im ken haya bo mum. When did we allow the
first case? If the Jew responded to the non-Jew and said, oh,
it's not acceptable unless there's a מום. mum, אבל אם אמר ליה
ייעשה בו מום, Aval im amar lei ye'aseh bo mum, we can't
use it unless a מום mum is made in it, ייעשה בו
מום, ye'aseh bo mum, hint hint wink wink, unless a מום mum.
is made, so כמאן דאמר ליה זיל עביד ביה מום. kman de'amar
lei zil avid bei mum. It's as if he said to him,
he hinted to him that he should make the מום, mum, right?
Especially if he said unless somebody goes and makes it, but no,
that's not what he said, he said unless a מום mum, is
made. But if you say made, made sounds like by human agency
and it's too much of a suggestion. And therefore we wouldn't have
allowed it even the first time because then it would have been
considered לדעת, lada'at, לדעת של ישראל, lada'at shel Yisrael, and it would
have been like the ישראל Yisrael did it. כמאן דאמר ליה זיל
עביד ביה מום דמי. kman de'amar lei zil avid bei mum dami.
It's like he said go make a מום. mum אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, Rava said, מכדי, mechdi, one minute, let's take a look. ממילא
הוא, Mimela hu, either way you're saying it in the passive. מה
לי היה, Ma li haya, what do I care if you said
it if a מום, mum if there is a מום, mum מה
לי נעשה, ma li na'aseh, if a מום mum. is made. Okay,
נעשה na'aseh can mean made by itself, you know, made by the
animal going against some barbed wire. אלא נעשה נמי ממילא הוא, Ela
na'aseh nami mimela hu, and even if you said made, it would
not be considered like it was your suggestion and he was doing
it at your behest. Okay, but yes, Michael, the point would be
if there were a case where you said unless somebody were to
make a מום mum. in it, right? I mean think about by
the way, by שבת, Shabbat, that's the way it works, you know,
by שבת Shabbat you can do the אמירה לעכו''ם amira le'akum on
שבת Shabbat is if you sort of just say, you know, oh,
it's dark in this room, it would be so nice if we
had light in this room, right? As opposed to
that's not considered, right, to be an אמירה, amira, if as opposed
to that's like a רמז. remez. But if you basically
said, you know, it would be so wonderful if somebody would turn
on the light, then that's, then that's different. So that's the type
of distinction... wait a minute, that's the type of distinction being made
here. So if it somehow is understood to be, you're right, in
both cases it would seem, look, that's the problem about this case
in the first place, which it seems that the non-Jew is doing
it intentionally for the sake of making it מותר, muttar, and the
גמרא Gemara is still distinguishing the first case from the later case.
So if we consider... so, you know, I really don't know, you're
right, at some level does it really matter if he's doing it
for the sake of the Jew or not for the sake of
the Jew? What really matters is if he's doing it to make
it מותר muttar or not. But somehow, even in a case where
he wasn't doing it to make it מותר, muttar, if he was
doing it, it was seen as doing it as a type of
a שליח shaliach for the Jew, right? So therefore that would make
it forbidden because then the Jew's desire to have it done is
what becomes relevant.
But there are two cases. One case he's doing it to benefit
the Jew, but it's not seen to be at the Jew's behest
or at the Jew's hinting, so it's not he's seen as much
of a שליח shaliach as much as just doing the guy a
favor, and that would not be a problem, right? As opposed to
if it's seen as the Jew dropped a hint and at his
behest, then basically it's like the Jew did it and therefore that
would, and therefore that would be a problem because that was the
Jew's intent. Wait a minute, I mean, is it not the
case?
I mean, like a non-Jew, you know, I hear you're in the
dark here, you know, I'm going to turn on the light so
you can now read your book. I thought didn't he used to
have to go out out of the room?
Okay, so there's two issues. One is an אמירה amira issue and
the other is a הנאה hana'ah issue. Even without your—this is a
totally different discussion—but even without your request, you cannot be נהנה neheneh
from a מלאכה melachah that a non-Jew does for you on שבת
Shabbos for your sake, even without your request. But there are exceptions
to that rule. There are times where the הנאה hana'ah is not
considered to be problematic and so on, so there are some exceptions.
Okay, whereas in terms of the issue about אמירה, amira, there there's
a difference of whether you're sort of dropping, you know, dropping hints
directed at that person or just describing the situation. But yes, there
is a second question about getting הנאה hana'ah from it, which even
if you didn't, even if it was not at your behest.
So what's the difference over here then? Here you are allowed to
get הנאה?
hana'ah? Whatever, because the problem about הנאה hana'ah by שבת Shabbos is,
yes, is different than the concern here. This is very much קנס
knas oriented. Yes.
But is there anything else?
I mean, like a non-Jew kicks a
beast and there's no actual
damage, there's no actual damage. היזק שאינו ניכר.
Hezek she'eino nikar. Yes, so what about on שבת Shabbos or something
like that?
So that's a different question, but that's, yes, the question about that's
about physical damage of objects. About people, but people, but there is
a concern as well there because by people there are things like
things that are not about their physical loss, about their suffering and
so on. But no, but unfortunately that also is only when it
gets wrapped together with a act of physical damage, then you pay
for other related damages as well.
So yeah, it's you really can't collect damages for straight libel and
defamation, although it's אסור assur because of לשון הרע Lashon Hara and
other types of things. Anyway, something to look forward to when we
get to בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, which is only five years away
or so. Okay, so now we go on. זה הכלל כל שהוא
לדעת אסור, Ze haklal: kol shehu l'da'at assur, this is the principle:
anything that's done intentionally is forbidden. לאתויי מאי לאתויי גרמא. L'atuyei mai?
L'atuyei grama. What does it include? It includes even indirect. Remember we
learned that yesterday, with like the little ear קרעכלאך crack-lach that you
made for the dogs, so that even though you didn't directly do
it, since you intended it, then we are going not only is
that forbidden, and we learned yesterday that that was part of the
biblical prohibition, we're also going to fine you and say that you
cannot benefit from the blemish. שלא לדעת Shelo l'da'at unintentionally is permissible.
לאתויי מסיח לפי תומו, L'atuyei masiach l'fi tumo, which would seem obvious,
which would mean that not only if you're not answering to this
non-Jew, but let's say you're just having a conversation with your friend.
'Oi, you know, when is this animal going to get a מום
mum. already, it's been around for ten years,' and the non-Jew hears
you and goes ahead and does it, that's also okay, which would
seem obvious. I mean, if you even even after a direct response,
it's allowed, why you have to tell the case of מסיח לפי
תומו masiach l'fi tumo is not so clear. Okay, but now we
go on. Anyway, that is definitely challenging to understand how the first
case with the non-Jew was considered to be שלא לדעת, shelo l'da'at,
but what I think is particularly interesting is the question as I
said about whether this is a policy or a fine and the
fact that we don't allow it when the non-Jew did it intentionally,
starts doing it intentionally, you know, to call that a fine is
a little bit of funny and it does push us a little
bit more into policy. Okay, let's take a look. היה בכור רודפו,
Haya bechor rodfo, let's say a בכור bechor, was running after you,
it was a ram. Right? We often think about it as this
nice cute little animal, but of course if it doesn't have a
blemish it can grow up to be a big ram. Okay, so
this ram is now running after you. בעטו ועשה בו מום, Be'ato
v'asah bo mum, you kicked it, okay, to get it off of
you and you made a blemish. הרי זה ישחט עליו. Harei zeh
yishachet alav. Then you can shecht on it, that was not intentionally
for the sake of making a blemish, okay? And maybe we're also
not concerned that maybe that was, you know, that was a hidden
intent either. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפא לא
שנו אלא שבעט בשעת רדיפה. Amar Rav Papa: Lo shanu ela shebe'at
b'sha'at redifa. That's only if you kicked it when it was running
after you. אבל אחר רדיפה, Aval achar redifa, if after it stopped
running after you and you kicked it out of anger, after the
fact, אסור. assur. Then you cannot. Why? Because then we are maybe
concerned that you're doing it for the sake of making a מום.
mum. Okay, no. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. מהו דתימא Mah d'teima? מהו דתימא
צעריה הוא דמדכר, Mah d'teima: Tzayreh hu d'madkar, that you're remembering your
צרות, tzaros, you know, your pain or whatever and you're just venting
and you're not doing it to make a מום. mum. קא משמע
לן Ka mashma lan that we're concerned that you're doing it to
make a מום. mum That's one version.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others
say, אמר רב פפא לא תימא בשעת רדיפה אין אבל שלא בשעת
רדיפה לא.
Amar Rav
Papa: Lo
teima b'sha'at redifa in, aval shelo b'sha'at redifa lo.
Don't say only when it's running after you, but after it ran
after you it does not apply. אלא אפילו אחר רדיפה נמי. Ela
afilu achar redifa nami. Even if you kick it after it runs
after you, it's also not considered to be for the sake of
a מום. mum, מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? צעריה הוא
דמדכר. Tzayreh hu d'madkar. You're remembering your pain and you're suffering and
and your anguish and you're just venting your anger on this on
this animal. And therefore, why it might not be a nice thing
to do to this innocent animal, but nevertheless it is not done
for the sake of a מום. mum אמר רב יהודה מותר להטיל
מום בבכור קודם שיצא לאוויר העולם. Amar Rav Yehuda: Muttar l'hatil mum
b'bechor kodem sheyetze l'avir ha'olam.
Now we're going to tell you about a way, remember way at
the beginning we spoke about selling the ear and the תוספות Tosafot
actually said that that went from the גמרא Gemara from being אסור
assur or not not- frowned upon to being a מצוה, mitzvah, because
since, you know, in the שלחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, because since now
we can't deal with בכור, bechor. better to solve the problem at
the outset rather than have to deal with misusing it. Here the
גמרא Gemara is giving another solution. You can make a blemish before
it has totally been born. Now, one way is sticking your hands
inside of the womb, but the גמרא Gemara. has a slightly easier
way, which is as it's emerging and the head is emerging, before
the majority of the head has come out and it's considered halachically
born, you make a blemish on part of it. Now, how do
you do that? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, גדיא, gadya, here's how you
do it. If it's a גדיא, gadya, if it's a goat, באזני,
be-oznei, it's ears, right, a goat has long ears. So the ears
will come out before most of the head, and therefore you can
make it in the ears and you don't have to be worried
that the head was already come out. אמרא, Imra, if it's a
sheep, so therefore it does not have long ears, בשפתי, bisfasei, its
lips, right? Cut the lips and that won't heal. Right, remember the
famous story about the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash where he cut the
lip? Anyway, so cut the lips and that will come out first
before the majority of the head. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say,
אמרא נמי באזני, imra nami be-oznei, you can even do the ear
of a sheep, although it's not long. אימא דרך צד נפק. Eima
derech tzad nafak. So תוספות Tosafos says אימא eima does not mean
you can say, but it means definitely, if it came out by
way of the temples, so that the ears came out first or
some part of the ears was exposed, as long as you're careful,
it's possible that you can get the ears before the majority of
the head, before it's considered born.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אכלה ולא מיחזי, achla velo michzi, if it
let's say has a blemish on the inside of its mouth, and
when it eats and it opens its mouth to eat you can't
see it, like some type of a cut on its palate or
something or the inside of its lip. However,
פעיה, pa'i, when it, what's it called, baas, no, it's grazes, bleats,
anyway, when it does that, ומיחזי, u-machzi, then you can see the
cut on the inside of its mouth. So a blemish is only
a מום mum, if it is externally visible. What does it mean
to be visible externally? Right, so you know, what if it's on
the inside of its ear, on the inside of its mouth? So
he says, if when it bleats, it's visible, that is considered... you
don't have to like open its mouth and look inside, then that's
considered to be externally visible.
It's internal, well, yes, but it's viewed, it can be viewed from
the outside understood in when it's doing certain activities. That's considered sufficient.
Okay, so that הוי מומא, havei muma, that's a blemish. ומאי קמשמע
לן, U-mai kamashma lan, what's he telling us? תנינא, Tanina, we taught:
החיטי החיצונות שנפגמו ושנגממו, hachittei hachitzonos shenifgemu veshenigmu, if you have the
incisors that have been like somehow
a cut or chipped or
cut
down. הפנימיות, Hapnimiyos, or the molars, which are more inside, שנעקרו, shene'ekru,
that were completely ripped out, those teeth, those are considered מומים. mumim.
So now why is it that the inner molars are considered מומים
mumim if they're totally ripped out? Who can see that the inner
molars are missing? So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? לאו
משום, Lav mishum, it must be, דכי פעיה מיחזי, dechi pa'i machzi,
because when it bleats, if it was only a little bit cut,
you wouldn't see it, but if it's totally been removed and it
bleats, you can see that the molars are missing. So you see
that that's defined as outwardly visible. So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Papa, רבא נמי טעמא דמתניתין מפרש, Rava nami ta'ama demasnisen mifaresh, you're
right, he's not telling us anything not in the משנה, Mishnah he's
telling us פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah, What's the explanation? Why
is it that those things that are deep inside are considered to
be visible, so are considered to be external? מאי טעמא שנעקרו הוי
מומא, Mai ta'ama shene'ekru havei muma, why is when those molars are
taken out is it considered to be a blemish? משום דכי פעיה
מיחזי, Mishum dechi pa'i machzi, because when it bleats, that's enough to
make it considered to be externally visible. Ran out? All right, whatever.
Yes.
What about the blood clots, which were not visible?
Well, right, so the blood clots was a real problem. And the
way, the only way we explained that was, you know, תוספות Tosafos
sort of says since the only way you can save its life
is by making a visible מום, mum by letting the blood, it's
like that visible מום mum, was already made. Which you know, is
obviously a חידוש. chidush. I, what I suggested was that the גמרא
Gemara. is not exactly saying that the blood clot is a מום,
mum. but what it's saying is that if the prohibition is only
to make a מום mum. when it's תמים יהיה לרצון, tamim yihyeh
leratzon, so something that will never be able to be תמים יהיה
לרצון tamim yihyeh leratzon because it will die or it will have
a מום, mum. then that's not something that's prohibited. But yes, the
blood clot per se is not the מום. mum. You have to
do some translation to explain why it's like it has a מום.
mum Okay, so now that's that. So now the גמרא Gemara. goes
on, so that was, so first we established if you make a
blemish, you get fined if you do it intentionally. Questions about what
intentionally means and somebody else doing it, even if not, you know,
kids, the non-Jew, etc., even somebody that's not an adult. So again,
which really does seem to point much more to a policy issues
rather than a fine and a punishment issue. Nevertheless, they're also intentional.
And then the next משנה, Mishnah, what does define by intentional? Now
we get back to the fun discussion that we've had a few
times, and this really is the way in which there's a lot
of relevance to aspects of בכור. bechor. relevant to other areas of
הלכה, Halacha, which is trusting people. Who can you trust? Okay, who
can you trust that, now you have to be able to trust
somebody that not only that it's a blemish, a blemish you know
you'll get somebody to inspect it. You have to trust somebody how
did the blemish get there, right? Because if it got there through
an intentional act, we're not going to allow you to שחט shacht
it. So who can you trust about that? Let's take a look
at the משנה. Mishnah כל המומים הראויים לבוא בידי אדם, Kol hamumim
hara'uyim lavo bidei adam, any blemish that could be human-done. There are
some blemishes that are not possible to have been human like it's
missing a leg. I mean I guess you could see a leg
cut off but you know let's say it's clear that it was
born without the leg or that it has an extra leg or
something like that. There's some blemishes that cataracts of the eye whatever
there's some blemishes that clearly could not have been done through human
agency. So then we don't need to trust. But any blemish that
might have come through human agency, who can you trust? So let's,
that was done not intentionally. So it says,
רועי ישראל נאמנים רועי כהנים אינם נאמנים. Ro'ei Yisrael ne'emanim ro'ei Kohanim
einam ne'emanim.
Israelite shepherds are believed, כהנים Kohanim shepherds are not believed. Now there
is an ambiguity of the Hebrew which will be debated in the
גמרא. Gemara How can you read what רועי ישראל Ro'ei Yisrael means?
Two ways.
Does it mean it's shepherds of others or what if there is
Israel, right.
Is it, if the shepherds are Israelites, so who is the shepherd,
or whose, who are they shepherding for? Right. So, now it probably
actually is not such an ambiguity because it would probably be רועים
ישראלים Ro'im Yisra'elim as opposed to רועים כהנים, Ro'im Kohanim, meaning are
the shepherds Israelites or the shepherds כהנים, Kohanim, as opposed to רועי
ישראל Ro'ei Yisrael is shepherds of Israelites, רועי כהנים Ro'ei Kohanim is
shepherds of כהנים. Kohanim. You will notice that our משנה Mishnah, has
both. It says it's רועי ישראל Ro'ei Yisrael and then it has
רועים כהנים. Ro'im Kohanim. So anyway, right, so what, there maybe the
part of the question is what is the text of the משנה,
Mishnah, right? If it is סמיכות, smichut, if then it is then
it means who are the owners. If it is non-סמיכות, smichut, then
it means who are the shepherds. That will be debated in the
גמרא. Gemara אינם נאמנים. Einam ne'emanim. It says there if they're Israelite
they're believed, כהנים Kohanim they're not believed, because obviously it's the כהנים
Kohanim who benefit from it being a blemish. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, נאמן
הוא על של חבירו ואינו נאמן על של עצמו. Ne'eman hu al
shel chaveiro ve'eino ne'eman al shel atzmo. You can be, you're believed
regardless if you're Israelite or כהן Kohen on somebody else's sheep but
you're not believed about your own sheep. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer, Rabbi Meir says, החשוד על הדבר לא דנו ולא מעידו. He-chashud
al ha-davar lo dano velo me'ido. Anybody who is suspect is not
believed about something to testify or to be a judge. So we
are now going to unpack what the three opinions are. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi Yochanan
ve-Rabbi Elazar. So it's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. חד אמר, Chad amar, one says, רועי ישראל
בי כהנים נאמנים. Ro'ei Yisrael bei Kohanim ne'emanim. So that when it
says that Israelite רועים ro'im are believed, it means we're describing the
shepherds themselves. Israelite shepherds in the house of the כהנים, Kohanim, it's
the כהנים's Kohanim sheep, but it doesn't matter, you're the Israelite and
it's you're testifying. So therefore you're believed. Now why would you believe,
it's not your sheep, what do you stand to gain? Well of
course you stand to gain because if your master is a כהן
Kohen and you say that this thing happened by itself, you might
you know, he might give you a little treat and little, you
know, little thing on the side. So no, we're not concerned about
that. לגימא לא חיישינן. Legima lo chaishinan. We're not concerned that he'll
feed you like from some of, you know, he'll שחט shacht the
בכור, bechor, thank you very much, I'll שחט shecht the בכור, bechor?
and by the way, why don't you join me tonight for a
steak dinner. Okay, at lamb chops. We're not concerned about that, okay,
that you would not compromise your integrity since you're only getting a
little bit of a benefit. Okay, you do have a price, right.
Okay, anyway. So, רועי כהנים בישראל, Ro'ei Kohanim be-Yisrael, however, if it
is a כהן Kohen shepherd in the house of a Jew, אינם
נאמנים, einam ne'emanim, they're not, why? It's not their בכור. bechor. מימר
אמר Meimar amar because the כהן Kohen. who is the shepherd figures,
כיון דקטרחנא
ביה, keivan de-katarchana bei, look, I was the one that worked, you
know, with shepherding this animal. So, and he's now he has to
give it away to a כהן. Kohen What other כהן Kohen is
he going to give it to? Of course he's going to give
it to me. I'm his faithful shepherd. לא שבק
לי בדידי ויהיב לאחריני. Lo shavik li bdidi veyahiv leachreini. He's not
going to ignore me and give it to somebody else. So since
he thinks he will be the beneficiary of the entire sheep, therefore
he cannot be trusted. So it has to do with if the
person himself is testifying is an Israelite or a כהן Kohen even
if they're not the direct beneficiary, where it's what they think that
they might get out of it. Okay, okay. והוא הדין, Ve-hu ha-din,
now once we're saying that you cannot trust a כהן Kohen for
a, for a
Israel's sheep, כהן לכהן, Kohen le-Kohen, you can't trust a כהן Kohen
for another כהן's Kohen. sheep even if he's not the shepherd. Why?
So Michael and I are both כהנים. Kohanim. I'm going to testify
about Michael's sheep. Now I have no thought that Michael's going to
give me his sheep. It's his sheep. He's going to keep it
for himself. He's a כהן. Kohen By the way, a כהן Kohen
as opposed to פדיון, pidyon, a כהן Kohen when it comes to
בכור בהמה bechor beheimah has to actually treat it as a בכור.
bechor There is not an exemption, there's, okay, there's an exemption for
a כהן's Kohen firstborn son, there's a כהן Kohen for a firstborn
of a חמור, chamor, there's not an exemption for a firstborn sheep.
So Michael's a כהן Kohen here, he has a firstborn sheep, he
has to bring it as a קרבן korban which he can't, so
he has to want there to be a מום. mum So I
go ahead and I testify it's got a מום. mum So Michael's
going to say thank you very much. give it to me, he's
going to keep it for himself. But what should we be concerned
about? That if I'm believed to testify for Michael, next time around,
Michael will return the favor. חשינן לגומלין, Chashinan l'gomlin, we are concerned
for reciprocity,
okay? So therefore, because of that concern, a כהן Kohen is not
believed to testify for his
ישראל Yisrael master.
What, I mean, you're a shepherd and I'm not.
No, no, no, I don't have to be a shepherd. I'm not
watching your sheep. I'm just testifying, I'm a סתם כהן, stam Kohen,
I'm your next-door neighbor, okay?
But what if you're a כהן Kohen shepherd and I'm a כהן
Kohen non-shepherd?
It doesn't matter. So the point is the way he's reading this
is, an ישראל Yisrael is always believed regardless who the owner is,
a כהן Kohen is not believed whether he's the shepherd of an
ישראל Yisrael or whether he's just testifying about his next-door neighbor, because
he thinks that since he's a כהן Kohen and he can get
the בכור, bechor he'll one way or the other, the benefit will
be returned, the favor will be returned. That's what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says. ואתא רבן גמליאל למימר Va'ata Rabban Gamliel l'meimar says
נאמן הוא על של חברו ואין נאמן על של
עצמו, Ne'eman hu al shel chaveiro v'ein ne'eman al shel atzmo, says
no, no, no, you can be trusted even as a כהן Kohen,
I can be trusted on Michael's sheep, he's my next-door neighbor, if
he is, maybe even if he is the owner, I'm not concerned
about for small little potential benefits I'm not going to compromise my
integrity. When it's my own sheep, then I can't be believed, okay?
Everybody's got a price, but the small ones are not, that's not
a high enough price, right? Anyway, that's what he says. ואתא רבי
מאיר למימר Va'ata Rabbi Meir l'meimar comes along רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says החשוד על הדבר לא דנו ולא מעידו, Hachashud al hadavar lo
dano v'lo me'ido, no
כהנים Kohanim are suspect and therefore they cannot testify and they cannot,
you know, be in court cases and therefore a כהן, Kohen now
of course therefore they're never believed even on somebody else's. Now that
sounds like the first opinion, a כהן Kohen, can't be believed whether
he's a shepherd, whether he's the next-door neighbor. So the גמרא Gemara
will explain how this is a different opinion, slightly different. That's one
approach which basically reads the beginning of the משנה, are you an
ישראל, Yisrael, you're believed, are you a כהן, Kohen you're not believed.
Now the גמרא Gemara, goes on, וחד אמר, v'chad amar, the other
approach says it's not whether you're a כהן Kohen or ישראל, Yisrael,
but who you are a shepherd for. רועי ישראל שהן כהנים נאמנים,
Ro'ei Yisrael shehen Kohanim ne'emanim,
shepherds of ישראל, Yisrael, of Israelites, even if the shepherds are כהנים
Kohanim are believed. Why is a כהן Kohen believed if it's the
Jew's flock? מימר אמר, Meimar amar, because the כהן Kohen says,
'Why would I lie for this Jew's flock? What, maybe he'll give
me the בכור? bechor No. לא שביק צורבא מרבנן ויהיב לדידי, Lo
shevik tzurba meirabanan v'yahiv l'didi,
he's not going to, you know, ignore a כהן Kohen. who's a
צורבא מרבנן tzurba meirabanan and give it to me, an ignorant כהן.'
Kohen Because who were the shepherds? The shepherds were not from the
rabbinic class. Of course, it makes it sound like the owner of
the sheep is, you know, interested in the rabbis and holds the
rabbis up, you know, with high regard, which wasn't also necessarily the
case, but anyway, this is through the גמרא's Gemara lens. So therefore
he figures, the כהן's Kohen. going to figure, 'I'm just a stupid
lowly shepherd. He's not going to give it to me; he'll give
it to a more important כהן.' Kohen, Okay, so therefore he's not
going to lie because he doesn't think he stands to benefit. So
therefore, if it's the ישראל's Yisrael sheep, you can believe the
shepherd. Okay. רועי כהנים והן ישראל, Ro'ei Kohanim v'hen Yisrael, now if
you're a shepherd of a כהן, Kohen even if you're an ישראל,
Yisrael, you're not believed. Why? Because then the כהן Kohen directly benefits
from your testimony. אינם נאמנים, Einam ne'emanim, why not דחיישינן ללגימה, Dechashinan
l'legima, because if I now testify that this כהן's Kohen. sheep has
a מום mum. as a, you know, happened naturally, he's going to
benefit and then he'll invite me for some lamb chops. So therefore
you're not believed. It goes by the owner. Okay? If the owner
directly benefits, we're afraid that it will be rewarded, and that's if
the owner's a כהן. Kohen If the owner does not directly benefit,
doesn't really benefit, we're not afraid that you will compromise
yourself. וכל שכן כהן לכהן דלא, V'chol shekein Kohen l'Kohen d'lo, and
certainly one כהן Kohen. cannot testify for his next-door neighbor כהן. Kohen,
Why? דחיישינן לגומלין וחיישינן ללגימה, Dechashinan l'gomlin v'chashinan l'legima, because we have
to be concerned in that case both for reciprocity and also maybe
he'll invite me over for some lamb chops. Okay, so therefore for
him the issue is not who is the testifier, but who is
the beneficiary. If the beneficiary is a כהן, Kohen then we don't
believe you, because then if he got some real benefit, we're afraid
that you'll get something back on the side. ואתא רבי שמעון למימר,
Va'ata Rabbi Shimon l'meimar, then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon completely rejects this
and he says נאמן הוא על של חברו ואין נאמן על של
עצמו, Ne'eman hu al shel chaveiro v'ein ne'eman al shel atzmo, no,
if you're testifying for somebody else, we're not concerned about those types
of that you might compromise yourself and it's not a problem. ואתא
רבי מאיר למימר Va'ata Rabbi Meir l'meimar then comes along רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and says החשוד על הדבר לא דנו ולא מעידו, Hachashud
al hadavar lo dano v'lo me'ido, and he says the really opposite
of the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, he says it's not about who
the who is benefiting, it's not about who you're testifying for, it's
about who you are. And כהנים Kohanim are generally suspect and ישראלים
Yisraelim are not generally suspect. It's all about the testifier, not the
testifiee if you would. Okay, so according to that, it's a nice
three-way debate, right? Is it about the person benefiting, is it about
the person giving the testimony, or is it basically you can always
testify for someone else? So let's, so let's take a look how
the גמרא Gemara now unpacks this.
בשלמא למאן דאמר רועי ישראל והן כהנים נאמנים, Bishlama l'man d'amar ro'ei
Yisrael v'hen Kohanim ne'emanim, so if you say, like we just said,
that you are believed if you are a כהן Kohen. if you're
testifying for an ישראל, Yisrael, meaning it goes about whether the person
who you're testifying about benefits. And therefore then היינו דאמר רבי מאיר
למימר. haynu deamar Rabbi Meir lemeimar. So therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
saying the exact opposite. החשוד על הדבר לא דנו ולא מעידו. hachashud
al hadavar lo dano velo meido. That it's the exact opposite. You
said that it goes by whether the beneficiary is a כהן. Kohen.
I, says רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, says it's whether the testifier is
a כהן. Kohen רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, I suspect כהנים. Kohanim.
כהנים Kohanim cannot be trusted about this. I don't trust a word
they're saying when it comes to בכור. bechor. Okay, he goes by
the testifier, whereas the first opinion looks at the particular context and
says, do you stand to benefit or not? Okay, that's the debate.
Okay, that makes sense. אלא... Ella,
אלא למאן דאמר רואה כהנים בישראל נאמנים. ella leman deamar roeh Kohanim
beYisrael neemanim. But according to the approach that said that the way
you read the משנה is if the כהן Kohen. is the shepherd,
he's not believed. So that's the same point as רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. It goes by the testifier. So מאי אתא רבי מאיר לאשמועינן?
mai ata Rabbi Meir leashmuinan? What's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir telling us?
היינו תנא קמא. haynu Tanna Kamma. It's basically what we already said.
It goes by if the testifier is a כהן. Kohen, So איכא
בינייהו דרבי יהושע בן קפוסאי. ika beinaihu deRabbi Yehoshua ben Kapusai. There's
still a basic difference. Because even the one that said that it's
when the testifier is a כהן, Kohen. okay, he still, concern was
because in this context you might benefit. Whereas, right, because you'll get
a little payback, a little reciprocity. Whereas רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position
was fundamentally כהנים Kohanim have no נאמנות. neemanus. They just can have
no, you know, they just completely are not believed in this category.
So here's a case where that will play out. Okay, the case
of רבי יהושע בן קפוסאי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Kapusai. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, רבי יהושע בן קפוסאי אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Kapusai omer, בכור בבית כהן, bechor beveis Kohen, צריך שנים מן
השוק להעיד עליו. tzarich shnayim min hashuk lehaid alav. Let's say you've
got a בכור bechor in the house of a כהן. Kohen How
can you prove that it is, what do you call it, how
can you prove that it's got a מום mum naturally? You get
two people from the marketplace, two people that are completely disinterested parties.
Now, two people includes כהנים. Kohanim. So here what you did is
you've got two כהנים Kohanim from the marketplace. So רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir would say, I don't care if it's two, I don't care
if it's a hundred, I just don't trust כהנים Kohanim about this.
Okay, whereas the first opinion was much more circumstantial and contextual. He
was concerned about payback, he was concerned about reciprocity. So if these
are number one, complete strangers, and number two, there're two of them,
that counteracts the concerns of some side deal going on. Okay, so
that would be the difference. That the first opinion, yes, suspects כהנים,
Kohanim, but only because in the context they might be rewarded. There
are cases where you're not concerned about that. They're strangers and they're
two of them. Whereas רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir categorically does not believe
כהנים. Kohanim. Yes.
So if, if they were, if a כהן Kohen can never be
trusted, then how can a כהן Kohen. with צרעת ever be... Okay,
excellent.
You are anticipating the end of the דף today before I get
to it tomorrow. Okay, so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, אפילו בנו אפילו בתו. afilu beno afilu bito. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says no, like you saw
in the משנה, you can testify as long as you're not testifying
for yourself, it's fine. Even to testify for a family member is
fine as long as you're not testifying for yourself. רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yossi omer, you know what is so refreshing about this גמרא,
Gemara right, that it doesn't live in this world of illusions that
everybody here is so פרום frum and כהנים Kohanim are פרום frum
or whatever. You know, it really understands that unfortunately the rationalizations and
the way people, you know, allow themselves certain license. Anyway, רבי יוסי
אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, אפילו עשרה והן בני ביתו אין מעידין לו.
afilu asara vehen bnei beiso ein meidin lo. No, I'm sorry. Maybe
you can testify for somebody else, somebody really different, but you cannot
testify for a family member. Even if there are ten of you
testifying like for one family member that his sheep got a מום
mum, in an innocent way, no, it doesn't matter. Family members are
totally out. Strangers okay, but not family members. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, כמאן אזלא הא דאמר רב חסדא אמר רב קטינא,
keman azla ha deamar Rav Chisda amar Rav Katina, ספק בכור שנולד
בישראל. safek bechor shenolad beYisrael. Ah, remember that? There are times where
an ישראל Yisrael could be a beneficiary. Why? Let's say this animal
was born and I don't know if it's a בכור bechor or
not, right? Could be, you know all those scenarios, I don't know
who the mother was and whether the mother had had a child
already. Okay, so I don't know whose it is. So what's the
הלכה? halacha? I keep it in my house. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero alav haraayah. And when can I eat it? When it
gets a מום. mum, So now testifying that this בכור bechor has
a מום mum. in for ישראל, Yisrael, the ישראל Yisrael is the
beneficiary because it was a ספק בכור. safek bechor. Okay, so now
who's believed? Let's take a look. Okay, so צריך שנים מן השוק
להעיד עליו. tzarich shnayim min hashuk lehaid alav. You need two people.
You can't trust a ישראל, Yisrael, you can't trust a כהן. Kohen
You need two people from the marketplace. So let's take a look.
We're going to unpack this. כמאן? Keman? Who is this going like?
רבי יהושע בן קפוסאי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Kapusai. Like רבי יהושע בן
קפוסאי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Kapusai that always says you need two and
they need to be strangers. Okay, so that's the first read. רב
נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says no, no,
no. Yes, I see that's what the ברייתא Braitah is saying, but
I don't buy it. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says בעלים מעידים עליו.
bealim meidin alav. Even the owners can testify. Why is it
different? דאי לא תימא הכי, dei lo teima hachi, מעשר לרבי מאיר
מי מעיד עליו? maaser leRabbi Meir mi meid alav? So how about
when I have my מעשר בהמה, maaser behemah, right? מעשר בהמה maaser
behemah every tenth animal. So if it gets a מום, mum I
eat it out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Who can I
trust? Now, now why are we saying לרבי מאיר? le-Rabbi Meir? Because
remember, if it's not לרבי מאיר, le-Rabbi Meir, לרבי מאיר le-Rabbi Meir
is the one that categorically does not trust the people that will
be the possible people that can benefit from this. If it was
somebody other than לרבי מאיר, le-Rabbi Meir, so if it was my
ספק בכור, safek bechor, Mike will testify, any stranger will testify, right?
You but you won't need anything special. But now we've got a
problem, right? Because according to לרבי מאיר, le-Rabbi Meir, you don't trust
כהנים Kohanim for בכור. bechor Okay, you don't now, because they're possible
beneficiaries. So therefore, when it's a בכור bechor, in the house of
a ישראל, Yisrael, who's a pos- so who's a possible beneficiary? If
Mike testifies for my בכור- bechor, ספק בכור safek bechor in my
house, maybe I'll res- maybe there'll be reciprocity. I'll testify for Mike.
Right? So now we're not going to trust anybody in the world
because it's a בכור bechor, in the house of ישראל, Yisrael, anybody
can have that scenario, so nobody should be trusted. Unless you say
אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, okay, we're going to say, oh,
but if that's true, how about a מעשר? ma'aser? If I have
a מעשר ma'aser and it's got a מום, who are we going
to trust? Right? Because anybody is a potential beneficiary, anybody could have
a מעשר ma'aser with a מום. So according to לרבי מאיר le-Rabbi
Meir that categorically doesn't trust people that are the potential
beneficiaries, right, who are you going to trust in that case? So
it says, מעשר- ma'aser so the גמרא says, no, no, מעשר ma'aser
isn't a proof. The גמרא says מעשר ודאי נאמן. ma'aser vadai ne'eman.
מעשר ma'aser definitely people are believed. Why? דאי בעי שרי ביה מומא
בכולי עדרי. de-ee ba'ei sharei bei muma be-chulei edrei.
Because if מעשר ma'aser you wanted to cheat, you would have put
a מום in your animal before you took the מעשר. ma'aser. So
therefore, since there's always a way that if you were being devious
you could have done it, we're not afraid that you're lying, okay,
because if you wanted to lie you had other ways of doing-
of getting out of it with- by being honest. אלא, ספק בכור
לרבי מאיר מי מעיד עליו? safek bechor le-Rabbi Meir mi me'id alav?
Fine. So let's go back to this case. According to לרבי מאיר
le-Rabbi Meir though, if you don't trust כהנים, Kohanim, so let's not
trust ישראלים Yisraelim because they're beneficiaries of ספק בכור. safek bechor. And
then nobody can testify, so you can never eat a case of
a ספק בכור. safek bechor. וכי תימא הכי נמי, ve-chi teima hachi
nami, lest you say that's true, that you can never trust anybody
with a ספק בכור safek bechor because anybody is a potential beneficiary
of a future situation, דלית ליה תקנתא, de-leis lei takanta, there's no
way of fixing it. והתנן, ve-hatnan, we taught in the משנה, שרבי
יוסי אומר, she-Rabbi Yosei omer, חליפה ביד כהן פטור מן המתנות. chalifa
be-yad Kohen patur min ha-matanot. If you had two animals, one was
a בכור bechor, and you gave one to the כהן Kohen. and
one you kept, you didn't know which was which. So
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says that the one you kept, you don't
have to give the מתנות. matanot. זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim ve-keiva,
we won't review why that is. ורבי מאיר מחייב. ve-Rabbi Meir mechayev.
לרבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you do have to give the מתנות.
matanot. So he says you have to give the מתנות matanot means
you had a ספק בכור, safek bechor, you were able to שחט
shecht it and eat it, and you didn't have to give the
זרוע לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim ve-keiva to a כהן. Kohen So now
we've got the question. How according to לרבי מאיר, le-Rabbi Meir, right,
could you ever שחט a ספק בכור? safek bechor? Who is suspect?
It should be all ישראלים Israelites are suspect because anybody could have
that scenario. And we should therefore suspect anybody who would ever possibly
be compromised in their testimony about it.
What is- what is your case exactly? חליפה ביד כהן? chalifa be-yad
Kohen? What was it?
You had two animals, one was a בכור, bechor, one wasn't, you
gave one to the כהן and you kept the other. Okay, you
didn't know which was which. So the גמרא says, so let's just
finish this point. אלא שמע מינה, Ella shema mina, בעלים מעידים עליו.
ba'alei me'idim alav. כהנים הוא דחשידי אמומי, Kohanim hu de-chashidei a-mumei, ישראל
לא חשידי אמומי. Yisrael lo chashidei a-mumei. It is not about who
is a potential beneficiary. It is about a certain, you know, if
you would call cultural habit or attitude. כהנים Kohanim who generally are
in the פרשה parsha of getting בכור, you then they've been known
to be compromised, they know to- they've been known to fudge, they
basically take liberties, you can't trust כהנים. Kohanim. ישראלים, Yisraelim, which it's
only much more rare that they actually get to keep a בכור,
even when it's their own self-interest and even when it's their own
בכור, they are believed. So it's not about a question of are
you in the class of people who benefit. לרבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is saying, no, we know you can't trust כהנים Kohanim about this.
If you had a ישראל, Yisrael, even if he ממש mamash was
the direct beneficiary, he was testifying about himself, they- you know, normal
people will be honest when it comes to כשרות kashrus and whatever,
you don't distrust them as a class even though you are a
possible beneficiary. So just to repeat that point, we have a statement
which is a ספק בכור, safek bechor, do you need two people
from the שוק? shuk? And the question here became, at least according
to לרבי מאיר, le-Rabbi Meir, who says that we sort of dis-
you know, suspect people as a class, that class is only כהנים
Kohanim not ישראלים, Yisraelim, so it's possible לרבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
normally completely rejects כהנים Kohanim would trust a ישראל Yisrael about his
own בכור, his own ספק בכור. safek bechor. But there's another opinion
that says it's not about looking at people as a class, it's
looking about every circumstance. So yes, when you are a direct beneficiary
even if you're a ישראל, Yisrael, you need strangers to testify, you
can't testify for yourself. That was the other opinion, but we will
now continue with this idea of that distrusting כהנים Kohanim as a
class, which is what לרבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does and look at
the implications tomorrow.